A lot of people listen to this, and if I
go back, if I go back just over 10 years
in my life, I would have been sat
listening to this conversation in £7,000
of debt.
And I would have thought, God, like
becoming a millionaire, that's a that's
a million miles away.
No pun intended. I I To become a
millionaire, I'm going to have to earn
so much more money. And at the time, I
was working in call centers.
It would it would have just felt so far
away. And I say, you know, people are
struggling to feed their children, let
alone become a millionaire.
Is it far away for the average person?
>> It's far away if you don't know the
strategy. There's a strategy to getting
out of debt. There's a strategy building
wealth. There's a system.
>> How much of it is just earning more
money? Because when I have these
conversations on my show, I think the
surprisingly untouched territory is we
don't teach people how to become more
valuable so that they can earn more
money. A lot of it's about like index
funds or savings, whatever. But how much
of it is just like
I need to get
higher valued skills in the market.
>> We know for a fact that making more
money doesn't make you rich. So so
people can go, as I told you earlier,
like from $100,000, they can go from
50,000 to 100,000 and still be broke.
They can go from 100,000 to 200,000 a
year and still be broke. They can go
from 200,000 to 300,000 and still be
broke.
In the US, when you take households that
make $150,000
a year, one out of three of them are
still broke.
When you peel back the curtain and you
ask, why is that? Well, we know things
cost more, but we also know there's
massive lifestyle creep, right? You get
you get around other people who are
making more money, and then you spend
more money.
And the reality is these phones are
designed to get you to spend everything,
right? Today, with the algorithms,
there's better technology today than
there's ever been to get you to spend
more money.
And nobody wants you to spend money
once, they want you to spend money for a
lifetime, right? It's a lifetime value
of a a
So there's a battle for our income.
And everyone wants a piece of it. It
starts with the government. Like, you go
to work and you go to work at 9:00 and
you actually work from 9:00 to 12:00 for
taxes.
Now, this is an important lesson,
actually. The government doesn't ask you
to budget to pay taxes.
They take your taxes from you
automatically. They take social security
from you automatically. They They take
the money from you automatically because
they know you won't have anything to
give if they don't take it from you.
Then people work from 12:00 to about
3:00 for housing and food. And then from
3:00 to 5:00 for all the rest of all the
rest of things.
The people who build wealth in America,
and really all over the world, they do
something different. They keep the first
hour a day of their income.
>> What do you mean by that?
>> So, what that means is whatever you
earn,
you could be making minimum wage. You
could be making $20 an hour, $30 an
hour, $40 an hour. Whatever you earn,
the first hour a day of your income has
to go to you.
You're the first person who gets paid.
>> And you mean you have to save it, invest
it?
>> You have to invest it. So, how do you
invest the first hour of your day
without paying taxes?
The answer is you pay yourself first
using a 401k plan. So, if you have a job
with a retirement account, 401k plan,
you sign up and you use that plan. Now,
I can't just stop right there, right?
Because Because it sounds so simple,
like, okay, I'll use my plan. No, you
have to know the formula to using your
plan to be rich. We know, after 40 years
now, exactly what you need to do if you
want to be a millionaire. I can tell you
how to become a millionaire starting
your 20s so that you're done by the time
you're in your mid-50s.
You save a little 1 hour a day of your
income is 12 and 1/2% of your gross
revenue.
I went on online today to look at what's
the latest statistics with 401k
millionaires.
The new stats that just came out from
Fidelity. There are 654,000
people in Fidelity 401k plans that are
now millionaires.
>> What is a 401k?
>> Okay.
>> Because you know, we've got a lot of
global listeners.
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> There's different types of 401k in every
country.
>> So in the US, a 401k plan is a
retirement account. It is a retirement
account that the company has set up.
Right? And it allows you to put money
away tax deductible. They call it
pre-tax.
In [snorts] most countries, you have a
deductible retirement account. But it
depends on the country, too, right? Like
in Canada, it's a different type of plan
than it is in Australia, than it is in
Italy, than it is here in the UK.
Almost every country though has some
form of retirement account and has the
ability to put money away automatically.
Here's the problem.
And I'll use the US specifically because
it's where I do most of my work. In the
US, those who have a 401k plan,
the ones that are millionaires, what
they did, here's the formula, the exact
formula, they saved 14% of their gross
income.
And their employer had a small match on
top of that.
And then how they invested the money is
key because it's not enough to just put
money in these 401k plans, you have to
be invested for growth. And growth means
stocks. Right? So you have to have and
and the actual specific allocation in
these 401k millionaires I just talked
about was about 70% stock and 30% bonds.
Okay, now what are people doing that
aren't achieving this? Well, the average
American is saving maybe 3 or 4% maybe
5%
if they have a 401k plan. People who
don't have 401k plans in many cases
aren't even doing this. They can, they
can open up an IRA account, but in most
cases they're not doing that.
So the whole secret is
not budgeting,
not using discipline, having the money
move right from your paycheck.
Paycheck gets deposited automatically.
And then it moves the day it hits your
bank account automatically first for
retirement. Then later we'll talk about
building a security account, building a
dream account.
The key is that the money moves
automatically.
So in the United States now there's by
the way 24 million millionaires now. So
we've seen an increase of 8 million
millionaires to 24 million millionaires
in the US in just 20 years.
How did they do that?
There's two primary escalators to
wealth.
That is stocks
and real estate. And if you're not in
stocks and you're not in real estate,
you are being left behind.
>> When you say real estate, does that mean
having a mortgage and have owning a
house home?
>> It's owning a home or owning REITs.
>> REITs?
>> REITs. Real estate equity investment
trust. So that's another way to buy real
estate without actually having to own
the home, but you don't get the same
level of returns.
>> I mean this is this is one of the hot
topics of conversation we've had on this
show several times is many of my guests
that are
sort of financial advisers say that
owning a home is a bad investment.
I think from what I understood from the
research and from reading your books
that you feel differently
about that.
>> Yeah, I mean I I couldn't feel more
differently. When we look at where is
wealth created in the United States and
also abroad, it's in two places. It's in
home equity
and it's in the stock market. So when
you look at housing
and you take someone who owns a a home
and we'll talk about it. I know it's
hard to buy homes right now.
Uh but when you look at people who own a
home versus people who rent,
homeowners in America follow this for
one second. Homeowners in America are
worth 40 times more than renters. So,
the average homeowner in America today
is worth over $400,000.
>> But, this doesn't establish causation. I
That doesn't mean that buying a home
made them rich, right?
>> It actually does, and I'm going to go
through that here. So, the average
renter is worth $10,000.
Right? So, why why does buying a home
build wealth? And how much wealth in the
United States is now in home equity?
Wall Street Journal just ran an article
on this, came out 2 days ago. There's
$34 trillion now in home equity in
America.
This number has gone up 90% since before
COVID.
The other money
is in retirement accounts, which is
60-70% in stocks.
There's $45 trillion now
in retirement accounts. So, those two
things alone equal $80 trillion.
Right? Like, when you want to go like,
"Where are the breadcrumbs? Where is
wealth being created?"
It's right in front of us. Now, the
problem that we have in the United
States, but also look, we're here in
London right now. The problem we have in
so many cities is that real estate keeps
going higher and higher and higher.
And people's incomes are not keeping
pace with the cost of buying a home.
So, when someone comes on a show like
this and says, "Look, you don't have to
buy a home.
It's cost more to have a house than
rent. You You know, I I watched one of
the shows. I won't say who it was. It
doesn't matter. They all said the same
thing. Don't buy a house. You'll be
trapped. You'll have to pay You'll have
to pay real estate taxes, and you'll
have to pay insurance, and things
break." They go through all these
expenses.
And it makes it sound like, "Oh, yeah,
if I rent, it'll be cheaper."
No, who who do you think pays these
expenses when you rent?
You do. The landlord passes the cost of
these expenses on to the renter
ultimately. Why do they do this? Because
people who buy real estate buy it for an
investment. They buy it for an
investment. They're not They're not
subsidizing these costs.
So, it's a hard thing to hear and
especially when you're young. Like I
have a a son who's 22. He's in Chicago.
He's going to move to New York City.
It'll be extremely hard for him to buy a
place in New York when he starts working
right away. Just will be. He probably
won't for two or three years. A lot of
young people when they move to major
city, they can't afford to buy right
away. When I came out of college, like
you, I was in credit card debt.
I had $12,000 in credit card debt. I
remember opening up my bills and having
the room spin
and thinking, "I'm never getting out of
credit card debt. How am I going to buy
a house?"
But I did. And in fact, I didn't buy a
home when I was young by myself.
I bought a home with a best friend. So,
how did I get my first house? First
house we bought was a quarter of a
million dollars. We put 10% down.
And my best friend and I, Andrew, we
split that down payment. So, we each put
$12,500 down. This is how we scraped it
together. The house was complete
fixer-upper.
And we didn't have enough money to make
the mortgage payments, so we rented out
bedrooms. And we had friends rent
bedrooms and that helped us cover our
mortgage. We scraped it together and
that's what a lot of people do when
you're young.
But if you don't get in the game of
homeownership and you rent in your 20s
and you rent in your 30s, you're going
to turn around in your 40s and having
not been built any net worth.
When I wrote The Automatic Millionaire
20 years ago,
two things have happened since then.
The stock market has gone up in 20 years
600%
>> Mhm. Okay, so if you had a
$100,000, just that is gone to $600,000.
If you bought a house, the house has
gone up 400%.
So when you read this book with all
these there's a whole chapter of updated
success stories.
There are a lot of ordinary people that
started saving 5, 10, 15, $20 a day,
bought a starter house, and today
they're millionaires.
>> So
am I not better off renting
and
investing in the stock market
versus buying a house?
Because obviously when I when I when I
buy a house, I'm paying a premium on the
house so that I can get a mortgage.
>> I want to bust this myth because what
happens is people come out and they go
the stock market I can tell you right
now the stock market over the last 20
years has averaged over 10% annually.
People go the returns are better in the
stock market than in real estate.
Yeah, but that's not apples to apple
comparison. Why?
When you buy a piece of real estate,
when you buy a home
people don't typically pay cash for
their first house.
They put down 20% and they borrow the
other 80%. So you take like an example
of a take a $200,000 home.
$200,000 home you put 40 grand in.
Home goes from 200,000 to 400,000
in 10 years. This has happened to so
many people in the last 5 years. Since
COVID there are markets all over the US
where housing prices have gone up 100 to
200%. So a person buys a $200,000 home,
they borrowed 80%, it's doubled, so
they've made 200,000 in profit.
They didn't put in 200,000, they put in
40.
So they got a five times return on their
down payment. They go to sell their
house
they don't pay taxes on the gain.
Because when you own a home, at least in
the United States, you own a home for
over two years if you're single, you get
$250,000 in tax-free gains. If you're
married, you get over half a million
dollars in tax-free gains. You get tax
deductions on the mortgages. So,
what happens is people come here and
they go, "You know what? You shouldn't
be You shouldn't be tied down. You need
to be flexible when you're young. You
don't want to have the responsibility."
And you should take the extra money and
you should put it in a mutual fund. And
you know what happens in the real world,
Stephen? People don't do that.
They rent an apartment that's nicer than
what they can afford, and they spend all
their money. And then they turn around
in their mid-30s, and they have no
equity cuz they haven't bought anything,
and they also haven't saved money.
It is an absolute freaking myth
that people take this extra money that
they could have used to buy a house, and
they're going to put it in the stock
market. They don't do that. And that's
why, also by the way,
corporate America got into the game of
buying up real estate all over America,
houses, and building apartments to rent
to an entire generation, hoping [snorts]
these people never buy.
This like 10 days ago, Trump came out
and basically said he wants the
institutions out of buying up all the
homes in America.
Why does he want to do that? Because he
cuz he recognizes
how serious of a problem it is to have a
generation of Americans who are renters.
I'm telling you, when you look at
average Americans aver- I'm talking
about ordinary Americans, when you look
at where their wealth is, it's in home
equity, and it's in the stock market.
And this is the last thing I'll say.
Generational wealth is created,
for better or worse, through home
equity.
So, when you look at what you you asked
the question about causation.
If a family doesn't buy a home,
the likelihood the next generation can
buy a home is very low.
Because it's the when the someone dies,
the money that is in the house, that
home equity,
is often what transfer transfers to the
next generation, helps the next
generation buy a house.
>> I was looking at some stats here cuz I
want to what I want I I wish I could say
sit down all of the guests that have
been on my show that have had a
difference of opinion and if said that
buying a house is a bad investment.
>> be a really interesting conversation,
right?
>> be a really interesting conversation.
What I've done as an alternative to that
approach is I've pulled up what they've
said. And I'm going to give you some of
the things they've said just so so you
can rebuttal them um and have your say
on them. One of the things that they
often say is that long-term real
inflation-adjusted home price
appreciation in the US is about 1%
annually. And one of my guests cited
Robert Shiller as the evidence of that.
After maintenance,
and which usually equals 1 to 2%, and
property taxes, which equals about 1%,
insurance and transaction costs, the net
real returns approach roughly zero on
average.
So, when you say housing is a great
investment, are you referencing the
gross appreciation, which is the
the total appreciation, or the net
returns after taxes, maintenance,
insurance, and selling costs?
>> So, when you dig into these kind of
numbers like this,
what they are is they're numbers, but
they're not real world. Right? So, like
when you when you talk to someone who
owns a home today and they've owned it
for 20 years,
and you ask them,
"How much of your net worth is now in
the equity in your house?"
Over 50% of their net worth is in their
house.
You will see people on your YouTube
channel that literally, if you read the
comments, and I'm sure you do,
>> I do, yeah.
>> where people say, "It's not true. There
was I read a comment yesterday on your
YouTube page. All I know is
I bought a house and it's gone up in
value three and a half times and the
rent when I bought the house was $1,200
and the rent today to buy that if I had
that house
if I was renting it would be $4,000.
So, the thing is you have to understand
is that rents always go up, Stephen.
Like I live in New York City for 18
years.
When I moved in New York City in 2001
a really nice apartment
a nice apartment was like $6,000 a
month.
When I left New York, that same
apartment was $25,000 a month.
Follow the Follow the insanity of that
math. Now, that apartment went from
being
a $2 million apartment to a $5 million
apartment. So, I could have been
[clears throat] renting it, but in my
case I owned it
and it went up in value $3 million.
So, I have friends who have been renting
in New York for 20 years. They have
built no net worth. I have no vested
interest in this conversation, meaning I
don't sell real estate. I'm not a real
estate agent. I'm not selling real
estate.
I've just seen in the real world how
people have built wealth. The The The
The McIntyres in this book, The
Automatic Millionaire, when they came
into my office and they were worth $1.8
million
and he was 52 and able to retire having
earned an average of $40,000 a year
all their money wasn't in the stock
market. They had bought a home in San
Leandro, California. What he What they
called a middle-class neighborhood.
Their home at the time was worth about
$300,000.
They had paid their mortgage off and
they had bought one more house on their
street. They rented the first house.
They bought a second house on their
street. They paid that mortgage off.
And so, they owned two homes free and
clear.
One house they got income from. One
house they lived in with no debt, and
then they had saved money in their 401k
plan.
>> So, if I was uh a young person or might
be a young person, a middle-aged and
older person
who took my down payment that I was
going to pay into the house, if let's
say it was say my down payment was
$20,000, and I put that into the S&P 500
instead,
over the long run, won't that grow
larger than the total home equity
potentially?
>> Here's why the index fund theory doesn't
work.
You can't live inside an index fund.
You [snorts] can't live inside a mutual
fund. You have to live somewhere as long
as you're alive. Here's what people
should do.
Take a look at what you're paying in
rent.
Now, ask yourself a question.
If I'm paying 5,000 a month in rent,
which lots of people are, right? Do you
know people paying 5,000 a month in
rent?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. So, they're paying 60,000 a year.
Let's take that number.
>> Yeah.
>> So, over 10 years it has been $600,000
in rent.
>> Yeah.
>> If the rent doesn't go up.
>> In 20 years they're going to spend 1.2
million in rent
if the rent doesn't go up.
In 30 years they will have spent
$2 million in rent if the rent doesn't
go up. But, the rent does go up.
So, the question you just have to ask
yourself is am I going to take all this
money that I'm spending on rent and
never build anything?
And if you really believe that renting
is better than owning,
then you should still consider the idea
of buying something then that somebody
else rents.
Cuz I promise you somebody's getting
rich in the transaction.
If you're the renter, you're not the one
who's getting rich in the transaction of
renting.
It is a great short-term solution
>> [snorts]
>> It is not a great term long-term wealth
building solution.
>> If you love the Dave Ramsey brand and
you watch this channel, please do me a
huge favor, become part of the 15% of
the viewers on this channel that have
hit the subscribe button. It helps us
tremendously, and the bigger the channel
gets, the bigger the guests.